Good morning. Today's דף daf is ס"ג Samech Gimmel 63 and we
pick up at the very bottom of ס"ב עמוד ב' Samech Bais
Amud Bais and we pick up from תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan about
five lines down. So we've been dealing with the two goats and
the drawing of the lots, or sort of doubling back to that,
this time emphasizing that their two goats look the same. We ended
with the point that the requirement of looking the same also applies
not just here, it applies by the two lambs on Shabbat, it
applies by the מצורע metzora in a few places, but nevertheless here
it is particularly underscored but in the sense of it's not just
a general appearance of the same, but same height, same cost, purchased
at the same time. So even though we have parallels elsewhere, it
really is a very heightened concern here. And now we go on
talking about really moving to a different topic and of which this
is an interesting application, which is the question of שחוטי חוץ, shechutei
chutz, the prohibition of שחיטה shechting a קרבן korban outside of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So let's take a look.
Hold on one second, this computer is acting a little funky on
me. Okay,
sixty-three, right?
Yep. Okay, so fifth line. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, right, fifth line.
שעירי יום הכיפורים ששחטן בחוץ, Se'irei Yom Kippur sheshachtan bachutz, so the
two שעירי se'irim of יום כיפור Yom Kippur that were שחט shechted
outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
so what's the
הלכה? halacha? עד שלא הגריל עליהם, Ad shelo higril aleihem, if it
is before they have done the הגרלה, hagralah, before they have done
the drawing of the lots, so either one in theory can be
used for something. Hold on one second, so that either one can
be used for, we'll see what they can be used for, but
at least their identity is not fully designated yet. So עד שלא
הגריל עליהם חייב על שניהם, Ad shelo higril aleihem chayav al sheneihem,
then if you שחט shecht either, you're חייב, chayav, because one of
the הלכות halachos is that you are only חייב chayav for שחיטה
shechting something that can be שחט, shechted, that can be brought in
the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. משהגריל עליהם, Mishehigril aleihem, once the lottery has
taken place, חייב על של השם ופטור על של עזאזל. chayav al
shel Hashem u'pattur al shel Azazel. You're חייב chayav for the one
to God, but you're פטור pattur for the one for עזאזל, Azazel,
because the one for עזאזל Azazel is no longer, what the phrase
is, ראוי לפתח אוהל מועד. raui l'pesach Ohel Moed. It's no longer
fit to be brought to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, because it's
going to go off לעזאזל. l'Azazel. I mean, it's sort of physically
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that's true, but it's not going
to be שחט shechted in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's not
going to be brought as a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, so you're not חייב chayav for שחיטה shechting it outside
of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
And is he exploring the possibility that the שחיטה shechita could have
been done before the הגרלה? hagralah?
No, it means,
no, you took, you, there were two goats that were purchased, you
haven't done the הגרלה, hagralah, somebody grabbed one of the goats, ran
outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and שחט shechted it. So if
you שחט shecht one of the goats before the lots have been
drawn, you're not חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. If the
lots have been drawn and then you grab a goat and hijack
a goat and take it out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and שחט shecht it, you're only חייב chayav for שחיטה shechting the
one that's של השם, shel Hashem, not the one that's לעזאזל. l'Azazel.
Okay,
okay, now let's take a look. עד
שלא הגריל עליהם
חייב על שניהם, Ad shelo higril aleihem chayav al sheneihem, that's a
real kidnapping. עד שלא הגריל עליהם חייב על שניהם, Ad shelo higril
aleihem chayav al sheneihem,
until you've drawn the lot, you're חייב chayav on either of them
if you שחט shechted it outside. למאי חזי? Le'mai chazi? What's it
fit for? אמר רב חסדא הואיל וראוי לשעיר הנעשה בחוץ, Amar Rav
Chisda: Ho'il v'raui l'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz, meaning what type of קרבן korban
can you bring this for? Before the lots have been drawn, it's
not fit for being brought for the שעיר להשם, se'ir Lashem, that's
only you're only able to bring it for the שעיר להשם se'ir
Lashem after the lots have been drawn, and you're not going to
be חייב chayav for שחיטה shechting it outside the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash until it is in a state where right now it's ready
to be brought. So right now before the lots, what can you
use it for? So he says, oh no, you can use it
for something, because later on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, we're going to
need another goat, we're going to need a goat that's going to
be brought on the outside, not outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
but outside the היכל, Heichal, in the עזרה, Azarah, right? And what,
and that is going to be the goat for the מוסף. Mussaf.
There's a קרבן מוסף korban Mussaf that's going to be brought today.
So even though the lots haven't been drawn and it's not yet
ready for the קרבן korban that we've been talking about, the blood
inside the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, at this stage, it's still fit
to be used for the קרבן מוסף. korban Mussaf. Okay, ומאי שנא,
U'mai shena, the גמרא Gemara says, one minute the גמרא Gemara says,
what do you mean it's fit for that? When we talk about
using this for the goat for the inside, for like the קודש
קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, we say it's not yet fit for that. Why
is it not yet fit for that?
דמחוסר הגרלה, D'mechusar hagralah, it's lacking the drawing of lots. לשעיר הנעשה
בחוץ נמי לא חזי, L'se'ir hana'aseh bachutz nami lo chazi,
but so you should by the same point say it's not fit
yet for being brought yet for the מוסף. Mussaf. Why not? דמחוסרי
עבודות היום, d'mechassarei avodot hayom, you haven't yet done all the עבודות
avodot of יום כיפור Yom Kippur until you do the קטורת ketoret
and the ox blood and the goat blood and the whole process
only then do you do the מוסף. Musaf. So it's not yet
fit for being brought as a מוסף Musaf either because it's lacking
a whole thing that has to come before it. One minute. So
קסבר רב חסדא, kasavar Rav Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda is
of the opinion אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום. ein mechusar zman l'vo
bayom. No, something that's going to happen later today, it's considered to
be fit for that. Since later today it could be used for
a מוסף, Musaf, even though right now it can't because it's too
early, you haven't done all the other stuff. Since later in the
day it could be used for a מוסף, Musaf, it's considered fit
for a מוסף, Musaf, fit to be brought in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash and if you checked it outside you're חייב. chayav. Now
of course the question is, so say that about being brought for
the goat on the inside, it's going to be fit for being
brought, the blood being brought on the inside for the קודש קודשים
Kodesh Kodashim later today, later today it'll be fit for that קרבן.
korban. Why do you have to go to the מוסף? Musaf? So
the answer is is that there's a difference. The מוסף Musaf is
basically just waiting. If you wait around, then they'll get to the
point where it's time to bring the מוסף, Musaf, whereas the being
fit for being brought inside the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, you need
to do something, you need to draw the lot, okay, and that's
called מחוסר מעשה, mechusar ma'aseh, it's lacking an action, it's not just
waiting, it actually needs something to happen to be done in order
to make it fit. Now you'll come back and say to me
but also bringing it for מוסף Musaf is not just waiting, you
need something to be done, you need all the other עבודות avodot
to be done. The difference is is that that's not done to
it, that's done external to it. Like other events will take place
and then this'll be fit. It'll be fit later today and those
other events are like you know somewhere else, you know, the bringing
of the קטורת ketoret and of the goat and of the and
of the ox. Fine, when those other events are done, this'll be
fit, it'll be fit later today, it's considered ראוי. ra'ui. Okay, whereas
by using it for the blood on the inside, that's not other
events, you gotta do something to this to make it fit, you
gotta draw the lots on this to make it fit, and therefore
from that from the perspective of that קרבן korban it is considered
unfit. Yes, Charlie.
We haven't really talked about the מוסף, Musaf, מוסף Musaf of, where,
when it can be brought.
Correct. We are not yeah we're not up to that yet. But
for now we are just working with the assumption that you have
to wait because of the whole idea of order, you're right and
you can't intervene in the order and that you have to do
so so but we didn't go to discuss let's say you intervene
with the order for something that's way out of left field, what
would be the implications which is the issue of the מוסף. Musaf.
For now let's just take for granted that the מוסף Musaf does
have to come after all the other עבודות. avodot.
I would have thought otherwise because you give מוסף Musaf offerings all
the time.
תדיר ושאינו תדיר, tadir v'she'eino tadir, that's right. So we'll talk about
that, but that's correct. We're just going to take that for granted.
Okay, so that's the answer. Yes, these goats are not fit for
the קרבן korban of the normal יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן korban
on the blood on the inside. That's because something needs to be
done, the lots need to be drawn, need to be done to
it. But they are considered fit for being brought as a מוסף
Musaf because later in the day after other external events take place
it will be fit and something that will be fit later in
the day, that's considered fit right now and therefore you're חייב chayav
for that. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבינא.
amar Ravina. So רבינא Ravina says השתא דאמר רב חסדא, hasha d'amar
Rav Chisda, now that רב חסדא Rav Chisda said מחוסר הגרלה כמחוסר
מעשה דמי, mechusar hagrola k'mechusar ma'aseh dami, right, this is the other
side of the equation. From the מוסף Musaf perspective it's fit because
that's just waiting and that's just external events. From the קרבן korban
brought on the in the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim it's not fit
because it's lacking the drawing of lots. So what's implied is that
that's a different type of a problem. That's not just waiting, that's
מחוסר מעשה. mechusar ma'aseh. It's lacking an action done to it, okay,
and therefore that's considered that's considered to be, not drawing the lots
is considered lacking a מעשה ma'aseh and therefore it's not fit for
that. So so so that's what he says. השתא דאמר רב חסדא
מחוסר הגרלה כמחוסר מעשה דמי. hasha d'amar Rav Chisda mechusar hagrola k'mechusar
ma'aseh dami. הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. ha d'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel. שלמים ששחטן קודם שנפתחו דלתות ההיכל פסולים. shelamim sheshachtan kodem
sheniftachu daltot haheichal psulim. If you slaughtered a שלמים shelamim in the
morning, any morning, right, early in the morning before they've opened up
the doors of the היכל, heichal, it's invalid, שנאמר shenemar ושחטו פתח
אהל מועד. u'shchato petach ohel mo'ed. It says by the שלמים shelamim
you shall slaughter it by the opening of the אהל מועד. Ohel
Mo'ed. So the אהל ohel doors of the היכל, heichal, not just
of the עזרה, azarah, you could be in the עזרה, azarah, but
the doors of the היכל heichal if they're not yet open, that's
the opening of the אהל מועד, Ohel Mo'ed, the שלמים shelamim is
no good. There's actually an interesting debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether
it applies to other קרבנות korbanot as well. But we're just now
going to focus on the שלמים. shelamim. So בזמן שהוא פתוח ולא
בזמן שהוא נעול, bizman shehu patuach v'lo bizman shehu na'ul, you can
only slaughter the שלמים shelamim when the doors of the אהל מועד
Ohel Mo'ed of the היכל heichal are open, not when they're sealed.
So top of ס"ג ע"א. samech gimmel amud aleph. If that's true,
שחטן בחוץ קודם שנפתחו דלתות ההיכל, shachtan bachutz kodem sheniftachu daltot haheichal,
if you slaughtered the שלמים shelamim outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
before the doors of the היכל heichal were open, פטור, patur, you'd
also be exempt. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? מחוסר פתיחה כמחוסר מעשה
דמי, mechusar pticha k'mechusar ma'aseh dami, the lack of opening the doors
is like the lack of an action. Meaning if you say that
they're not yet fit by our case by the goats for the
עבודה avoda of the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim because you haven't drawn
the
lot. something has not yet been done to it that makes it
fit. So he says then that would be, and therefore you're not
חייב Chayav if you שחטed shacht it outside. That's true also by
the שלמים. Shelamim. If they're not yet fit because some action hasn't
been done, the doors haven't been opened. Now of course there's a
big difference. You don't open the doors to define the שלמים. Shelamim.
You open the doors because you need to open the doors.
And for the עבודה Avodah it defines זמן. Zman.
Exactly. It sounds more like, it sounds more like the מוסף Musaf
idea. You have to wait for some external event, and then it'll
be fit. So there opening the door is an external event. It
doesn't define the nature and change the status of the thing the
same way the drawing of lots changes the nature and the status
of the animals. רש"י Rashi says, tries to make it work by
saying since the פסוק Pasuk says specifically by the שלמים, Shelamim, ושחטו
פתח אהל מועד, Ushchato Pesach Ohel Moed, it identifies the שלמים Shelamim
with פתח אהל מועד, Pesach Ohel Moed, that having the פתח, Pesach,
the reality of פתח אהל מועד Pesach Ohel Moed is something that's
definitional about the שלמים, Shelamim, is considered to be something that directly
relates to the שלמים. Shelamim. As opposed to our issue by the
מוסף Musaf where whatever is happening does not relate to it at
all, it's just something external. Okay, but it does seem like a
stretch. My gut would have been to say that this is more
like the מוסף Musaf waiting and less like the drawing of the
lots. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like goes on: ומי
אית ליה לרב חסדא,
Umi
Is
Lei l'Rav Chisda, does רב חסדא Rav Chisda really hold הואיל, Ho'il,
of this idea of הואיל, Ho'il, since you could, you know, that
since it's fit in a
different context it's considered fit? Even though this thing is supposed to
be the שעיר Seir that's שחטed shacht outside—I'm sorry, the שעיר Seir
whose blood is brought on the inside—since in theory it could be
used for the קרבן מוסף, Korban Musaf, therefore that's considered fit and
therefore you're חייב Chayav for שחטing shacht it outside. So that's the
idea of הואיל, Ho'il, that you don't go by
the defined identity of the thing alone, you also consider what it
could be used for in theory and that's relevant. So that's רב
חסדא's Rav Chisda position. So let me ask you this, that I'll
show you that it doesn't seem like he could say that. דהא
אמר רב חסדא, De'ha Amar Rav Chisda, because רב חסדא Rav Chisda
himself says: פסח
ששחטו בחוץ בשאר ימות השנה לשמו, Pesach she-Shachto b'Chutz b'She'ar Yemos ha-Shana
Lishmo, you have a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, again this is all
about שחוטי חוץ Shchutei Chutz today. You have a קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach that you slaughtered outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but
it was the rest of the year. Now as you'll know, if
you take a פסח Pesach the rest of the year and you
bring it as a קרבן, Korban, if you bring it as a
פסח, Pesach, it's invalid. If you bring it for anything else that
redefines its status and it becomes a שלמים Shelamim and it's valid.
So you have to do the opposite in order to make it
valid. So you took this פסח Pesach and you brought it outside
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, לשמו פטור, Lishmo Patur, if you
שחטed shacht it for the sake of a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
you're exempt. Why? Because that, had you done that on the inside,
it would have been invalid. So the way you brought this קרבן
Korban was not something that with this identity of a פסח Pesach
could be brought in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so you're exempt.
שלא לשמו, Shelo Lishmo, however if you שחט shacht it for a
שלמים, Shelamim, then חייב, Chayav, you're חייב Chayav if you do it
outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, because this identity now that you
have given it as a שלמים, Shelamim, with this identity it could
have been brought in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and therefore you're
חייב. Chayav. Okay, now one minute. He says: טעמא דשלא לשמו, Taama
de-Shelo Lishmo, the only reason you're חייב Chayav is because you did
it שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo and you redefined its identity to be
a שלמים. Shelamim. הא
סתמא, Ha Stama, if you didn't define it either way, you didn't
say לשמו, Lishmo, you didn't say שלא לשמו, Shelo Lishmo, לשמו
הוא ופטור, Lishmo Hu u-Patur, it would be defined as a פסח
Pesach and you'd be exempt. You could have just said the first
case of the ברייתא Braisa of the statement was if you do
it for a פסח Pesach you're exempt. But now the question is:
Why are you exempt even if you do it as a פסח?
Pesach? ואמאי? Ve'amai? Why should you get off the hook?
לימא הואיל וראוי לשלא לשמו בפנים. Leima Ho'il v'Ra'ui l'Shelo Lishmo bifnim.
Why don't you say: No, even if you do it as a
פסח Pesach you should be חייב Chayav because in theory you could
have done it שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo and have been a good
קרבן. Korban. He says: Look at the comparison. You're telling me you
שחט shacht one of these goats outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
even though they're designated for being brought into the קודש הקודשים Kodesh
Hakodashim or לעזאזל, l'Azazel, you're going to be חייב Chayav because whatever,
even though they have that identity and that's how they're supposed to
be used, you could theoretically use it for a different קרבן, Korban,
you could bring it for a מוסף, Musaf, and that's enough to
be מחייב Mechayev you. So say the same about a קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. You שחט shacht a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach outside the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you do it for a קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, you're פטור. Patur. Why are you פטור? Patur? Theoretically you could
have used it for a שלמים, Shelamim, just redesignate it.
The פסח Pesach is the opposite thing.
So the גמרא Gemara says: הכי השתא? Hechi Hashta? What type of
comparison is
that? התם בעי עקירה הכא לא בעי עקירה. Hasam Ba'ei Akira Hacha
Lo Ba'ei Akira. There you have to change its identity. Its identity
is a פסח, Pesach, so therefore you can't say: Well, you would
have been חייב Chayav had you brought it as a שלמים. Shelamim.
Its base identity is a פסח, Pesach, so therefore I'm going to
be exempt unless I am... The one that actually turns it into
a שלמים. shelamim. Then I've made it a שלמים shelamim and then
since that would be good inside I'm חייב chayiv now. But if
I don't do anything you don't say oh we're going to get
you because in theory you could have changed its identity. That only
means in theory you could have changed its identity. You would not
look at that case. Here by the goat, although you're intending to
use it inside the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, it does not really
have a קדושה kedusha that is defined in that unique way and
that's an interesting point. Its קדושה kedusha might be right now a
generic חטאת chatas or a generic קרבן קדושה. korban kedusha. Its specific
identity for the goat on the inside has yet to be defined.
That will happen when the lots are drawn. So to say that
I could use this for a מוסף musaf does not require saying
that I would change its basic identity. Okay. So again what we
are saying now is that רב חסדא Rav Chisda says these goat
you slaughtered outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's not fit yet
for for being brought in קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim and you're not
yet חייב chayiv and you're not you wouldn't be חייב chayiv for
that because it lacks the drawing of lots so that's considered unfit
for that for that role because it's מחוסר מעשה. mechusar ma'aseh. It
is though theoretically fit for a מוסף. musaf. Okay? But that's one
of the reasons it's theoretically fit for מוסף musaf is it hasn't
had the lots drawn on it and it could it really could
be used for a מוסף. musaf. It doesn't have any קדושה kedusha
any identity that defines it as not usable for a מוסף. musaf.
That is in contrast to slaughtering a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach outside
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash during the rest of the year where
there although you could make it fit you would have to change
its identity. And in its current identity it is not fit for
being brought in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and therefore you are
exempt. Yes.
Yeah what I'm trying to understand is I understand that it's lacking
the מעשה ma'aseh of a lot but what about the time it
was purchased, right? I'm the גזבר gizbar of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash I know I'm looking for two שעירים se'irim they're supposed to
be.
Right but that does not
define its קדושה. kedusha. Its קדושה kedusha remains generic until the drawing
of the lots. You don't have you know you don't have that
degree of specificity. Is the גזבר gizbar buying it? Apparently
I mean it's true but
apparently
you know let's say for example somebody had two sins. They ate
חלב chelev בשוגג beshogeg and they had חמץ chametz for פסח. Pesach.
And they have to bring a חטאת chatas for each one. And
they bring a חטאת chatas and in their mind they're thinking this
is going to be the one for חמץ chametz for פסח. Pesach.
Is there anything stopping them from bringing it for the other sin?
I mean how would the specificity of the identity you know of
the קרבן korban is
is a question.
If he bought it so he says okay I'm going to
decide later then fine but if he did decide? So I don't
think
so. We can't necessarily make all the
קדושות kedushos tailor-made. They're basic general categories פסח Pesach חטאת chatas שלמים
shelamim etc. Not you know not every subdivision you know is
necessarily its own category in terms of how it defines its קדושה.
kedusha. But actually I'll check up on that about the חטאת. chatas.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. רבה
בר שימי Rabba bar Shimi מתני להו בדרבה. masni lehu bederabba. So
רבה בר שימי Rabba bar Shimi taught both these teachings by רבה
Rabba that רבה Rabba said you're חייב chayiv because you could have
used it for a מוסף musaf but by a פסח Pesach you're
exempt but you're חייב chayiv for the goat. וקשיא דרבה דרבה. Vekashya
derabba derabba. The same way we had a question of how do
the two רב חסדא Rav Chisda work his question was how do
the two רבה Rabba work. Why are you חייב chayiv for the
goat outside and exempt for the פסח? Pesach? ומשני כדישנינן Umeshani kideshaninan
and he gave the same answer we gave. So basically it means
that he had the same סוגיא sugya except he had רבה Rabba
in the place of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Okay. כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי יוחנן Ki asa Rav Dimi amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Rabbi Yochanan when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said in the name of רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan פסח ששחטו
בחוץ בשאר ימות השנה בין לשמו בין שלא לשמו פטור. Pesach sheshachto
bachutz bish'ar yemot hashanah bein lishmo bein shelo lishmo patur. This example
you're giving about a פסח Pesach being slaughtered outside I would say
not only are you פטור patur when you slaughter it for a
פסח Pesach you're פטור patur even when you slaughter it for a
שלמים. shelamim. Why? Why don't you say that if you slaughter it
for a שלמים shelamim you're חייב chayiv because it could have been
brought that way in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? אמר רב דימי
אמריתה לשמעתא קמי דרבי ירמיה Amar Rav Dimi amrisi lishmayta kamei deRabbi
Yirmiyah I said this over in front of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah
so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah was one in whose name he was
saying it but he basically said you know I said this and
then I sort of challenged him on it and said the following.
בשלמא לשמו דהא לא חזי ליה Bishlama lishmo deha lo chazi lei
I get why you're exempt when you slaughter it as a פסח
Pesach it's not fit for being brought as a קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. אלא שלא לשמו אמאי Ella shelo lishmo amai why are you
exempt when you slaughter it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo out of the
בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? הא חזי שלא לשמו בפנים Ha chazi shelo
lishmo bifnim it could have been brought this way in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash as a שלמים. shelamim. ואמר לי Va'amar li he
said back to me עקירת חוץ לאו שמה עקירה Akiras chutz lav
shemah akira an act to redefine its identity doesn't work outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay. The idea that when you slaughter a
פסח Pesach for something other than a פסח, Pesach, when it's not
פסח, Pesach, it becomes a שלמים, Shlamim, that is when you're doing
the שחיטה shechita the right way, that's when you're bringing it correctly
as a קרבן. korban. That's where the מחשבה machshava said that a
פסח Pesach that is שחט shecht for some other purpose, its identity
changes when it's actually being brought הלכתית halachically as a legitimate קרבן,
korban, not when it's being brought outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So even though you're saying that you're making it a שלמים, Shlamim,
that is ineffectual, and at the end of the day, what you've
done is you've שחט shecht a פסח Pesach outside the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, so you're פטור patur because you שחט shecht a פסח
Pesach the rest of the year.
And you're פטור patur if you שחט shecht it by night, right?
So we had that idea. Right, I'm not talking about by night,
but כי אתא רבין אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי יוחנן, ki osa
Ravin amar Rabbi Yirmiya amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין Ravin came, he
said in the name of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya in the name
of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so the same tradition, except this is
רבין Ravin who's now saying it over, not רב דימי. Rav Dimi.
I mean, so, but רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiya, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
are the same, but he tells the version very different. Here's what
he says: פסח ששחטו בחוץ בשאר ימות השנה, Pesach she-shachato bachutz bish'ar
yemot hashanah, you שחט shecht a פסח Pesach outside the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash the rest of the year, בין לשמו בין שלא לשמו
חייב. bein lishmo bein shelo lishmo, chayav. Not that you're פטור patur
both ways, you're חייב chayav both ways. Okay? So we know why
you're חייב chayav when you שחט shecht it for a שלמים, Shlamim,
that's what we've been saying. Why are you חייב chayav when you
שחט shecht it for a פסח? Pesach? So he says: ואפילו לשמו,
va'afilu lishmo, ואפילו לשמו, va'afilu lishmo, even when you שחט shecht it
for a פסח, Pesach, you're חייב chayav outside the בית המקדש? Beis
HaMikdash? והתנן: ve-hasnan: מחוסר זמן, mechusar zman, this is something that is
lacking in time, meaning it's not yet the time to be brought,
בין בגופו, bein begufo, whether it's because of its own time, its
own biological time, it's too young, בין בבעלים, bein biba'alim, whether it's
because of the owner are not yet fit for bringing this קרבן,
korban, that you are exempt. If you bring a קרבן korban out
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and the קרבן korban is not
yet its right time, or you're not yet your right time for
the קרבן, korban, which makes the קרבן korban unfit, you are exempt.
Okay? ואיזהו מחוסר זמן בבעלים, ve-eizo mechusar zman biba'alim, what does it
mean it's not yet the time in terms of the owners? הזב
והזבה והיולדת, hazav vehazava vehayoledes,
a male זב, zav, a זבה, zava, a woman with a cycle
not during her menstrual period, a
יולדת, yoledes, childbirth, והמצורע, ve-hametzora, there's our friend the מצורע metzora again.
Okay, actually מצורע metzora isn't in the משנה mishna but the גמרא
gemara sort of adds it. So any of these
שהקריבו חטאתם ואשמם בחוץ, shehikrivu chattatam ve-ashamam bachutz, if they bring their
חטאת chattas and their
אשם asham outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash before their period is
up, פטורין, pturin, they're exempt because that's מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman. To
bring a חטאת chattas of a יולדת yoledes before her 40 days
are up, or a חטאת chattas of a זב zav before his
seven days are up, is not something that could be brought in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because it's not yet fit, even though
the owner hasn't spent seven days, but nevertheless, at this stage in
time, this קרבן korban cannot be brought in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. So then they would be, then you'd be exempt when you
bring it outside. However, עולותיהן ושלמיהן בחוץ חייבין, oloteihen veshalmeihen bachutz chayavin,
if you bring an עולה olah or שלמים shlamim (nobody here has
a שלמים shlamim except the גמרא gemara sticks in a נזיר nazir
that has a שלמים shlamim anyway). If you bring their עולה olah
or שלמים, shlamim, then you are חייב. chayav. Why? Because even though
the עולה olah and שלמים shlamim is brought together with the חטאת
chattas at the end of the (forget the שלמים) shlamim עולה olah
at the end of the seven-day period or however long the period
is, but if you bring an עולה olah earlier, right, an עולה
olah is much more generic, so an עולה olah could be brought
as a free will, it could be brought earlier, so if you
brought it earlier, it's not a problem. Okay, this is the issue
of sort of generic identity, right? So it could be brought earlier,
it's not a problem, but the חטאת, chattas, that can only be
used for its stated purpose, and therefore if it's not yet the
time, it is not yet fit. Okay? So ואמר רבי חלקיה בר
טוביה, ve'amar Rabbi Chilkiya bar Tuvia, now how is this relevant to
our issue of the פסח? Pesach? So let's take a look, we're
not yet done. Okay. So ואמר רבי חלקיה בר טוביה: ve'amar Rabbi
Chilkiya bar Tuvia: לא שנו אלא לשמו, lo shanu ela lishmo,
when is it that you are going to be exempt for the
חטאת chattas that's brought too early by these זב zav and זבה,
zava, when you do it לשמו? lishmo? I mean, when are you
going to be exempt for the חטאת chattas that's brought too early
by these זב zav and זבה, zava, when you do it for
their sake? When you do it for the purpose of the חטאת,
chattas, and then that's identity is a קרבן korban that cannot be
brought yet in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. אבל שלא לשמו, aval
shelo lishmo,
if you brought it for some other purpose, then חייב, chayav, then
you are חייב. chayav. Why? Because if,
I'm sorry, so this is not about the חטאת, chattas, this is
about the אשם, asham, because a חטאת שלא לשמו chattas shelo lishmo
is פסול. pasul. Okay, so this is only about the אשם. asham.
Because right, a חטאת chattas either way you can't bring it. If
you bring it לשמו lishmo it's not yet the time, if you
bring it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, a חטאת שלא לשמו chattas shelo
lishmo is פסול. pasul. But an אשם, asham, if you do it
לשמו lishmo it's not yet the time, but if an אשם שלא
לשמו, asham shelo lishmo, you know, then it is accepted, it's a
legitimate קרבן, korban, you don't fulfill your obligation, but it works as
a קרבן. korban. So he says, when is it true that if
you bring the אשם asham outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
the seven days or the period isn't up, that you're פטור? patur?
When you do it as an אשם לשמו, asham lishmo, but if
you do it שלא לשמו... shelo lishmo... and חייב chayav cause in
that situation it could have been brought in the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. So that seems to be good evidence that a פסח Pesach
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo would be חייב. chayav. It should be exactly
the same as an אשם שלא לשמו, asham shelo lishmo, right? Because
you have a קרבן korban that in its current identity cannot be
brought in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, but if you do it
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, you change its identity in a way that
now could be brought in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So if
that's true for the אשם asham before the seven days are up,
it should be true for the פסח Pesach even when it's not
yet פסח. Pesach. Okay, when you do it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo,
you've made it fit and therefore you should be חייב. chayav.
A חטאת chatas no matter what you do it.
A חטאת chatas you're always פטור patur because it can't be brought
now and it can't be brought right.
I have a naive question.
Wait, before your naive question let's see the answer, maybe it'll answer.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הכי השתא, hachi hasha, what type
of comparison is that? התם בעי עקירה, hasam bai akira, הכא פסח
בשאר ימות השנה שלמים נינהו. hacha Pesach bish'ar yemot hashanah shlamim ninnu.
The גמרא Gemara now says before we said that there's you know
that there's very strong reason to be exempt by a פסח Pesach
because it requires changing of its name and even suggested the idea
that you know עקירת חוץ לא שמו עקירה, akiras chutz lo shemo
akira, that when you do it לשמו lishmo you haven't changed its
identity because you have to change it in the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. But here we're actually going here we're going to say the
opposite. I'm not the opposite but we're going to say that it's
actually in some ways easier to change its identity. So remember what's
the question? The question is a פסח Pesach we're going we said
even when you did it even when you did it now I've
lost track. Okay.
Even when you did it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo outside the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash
you're חייב chayav because well one second
even when you did it לשמו lishmo outside the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash
hold on start this one more time. Okay.
This statement said that the פסח Pesach whether it's לשמו lishmo whether
it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo you're חייב. chayav. We understand why you're
חייב chayav when it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo because you've made it
into a שלמים. shlamim. But why are you but the question is
why are you חייב chayav when it's לשמו lishmo in this state
it's not fit for the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Okay that's the
question. And the גמרא Gemara gave a comparison to this הלכה halacha
about the אשם. asham. The אשם asham before it's fit for being
brought if you do it outside the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash so
it says that you are that you are פטור. patur. You are
חייב chayav if you do it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo you've changed
its identity but you are פטור patur when you do it לשמו.
lishmo. So why I might have said this wrong I might have
got a little bit mixed up there. So here the question is
why by the פסח לשמו Pesach lishmo are you חייב chayav and
by the אשם לשמו asham lishmo you're פטור? patur? Okay or the
חטאת לשמו chatas lishmo certainly you're פטור patur but the אשם asham
is the better comparison. Because why so why by the אשם asham
is this clear here or not?
Let me maybe do this. I have a sense that I'm losing
everyone myself included. Okay so everyone. Yes everyone.
Okay.
So here you have right
פסח לשמו Pesach lishmo this is not on פסח Pesach and פסח
Pesach right שלא לשמו shelo lishmo which when you do it שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo it becomes a שלמים. shlamim. Okay but in this
state it cannot be go to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Are
you חייב chayav or not? So we have three positions. We have
the first one who I forget whether who it was I think
it was רב חסדא Rav Chisda right was it רב חסדא Rav
Chisda who said you're going to be you're going to be פטור
patur here because it's not fit right and חייב chayav here because
it is fit for being brought in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
That makes a lot of sense. The next position we had in
the name of it was רב דימי Rav Dimi first in the
name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said said what? The next position
said you're going to be פטור patur in both. Okay now why
are you פטור patur here isn't this כשר kasher in the I'm
sorry keep on getting it wrong why are you פטור patur here
isn't this כשר kasher as a שלמים? shlamim? Yes but you're פטור
patur because of the because of עקירת חוץ לא שמו עקירה
akiras chutz
lo shemo akira meaning it's לא שמו עקירה lo shemo akira meaning
here it becomes a שלמים shlamim it becomes a שלמים shlamim in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash it becomes a שלמים shlamim because here
it remains a פסח Pesach and therefore you're פטור patur in both
cases. Okay that would be חייב chayav only if he
went to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and then went out right?
Yeah no you have to see
I mean if you did the זריקה zerika out.
When you one minute I'm sorry okay so now רב ירמיה Rav
Yirmiyah in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said חייב chayav
for both. Okay so we get חייב chayav here it's a שלמים.
shlamim. Why are you חייב chayav here? Why are you חייב chayav
when you do it לשמו? lishmo? That's the question. And this is
being contrasted to
the אשם asham because the אשם asham you have לשמו lishmo outside
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash before its time and שלא לשמו. shelo
lishmo. So this would be no good in the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash because it's before its time
but if it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it is good okay because
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it counts as a קרבן korban it doesn't
fulfill your obligation so we don't care that it's not the right
time.
So no good means
means a פטור patur this is פטור patur okay because it's before
its time but here by שלא לשמו... shelo lishmo... שלא לשמה shelo
lishma would be good. So and what's the הלכה? halakha? The הלכה
halakha is exactly what that ברייתא braita says, exactly what רב חסדא
Rav Chisda says. It's the same פטור patur and חייב. chayav. Okay,
the same thing here, the logical thing. Here it's no good, here
it's good, so it should lead to exactly the same thing. Now,
I think I still confused you. Meaning, this is a פסול pasul
and this is a כשר. kasher. And you
just said no good just means it's not fit. Alright, anyway, so
that's the question. Another way to just focus the question is what
we said by the אשם, asham, the same thing by the פסח
pesach as by the אשם. asham. So the basic question is, how
are you saying חייב chayav both? Shouldn't it follow what we know
is true by the אשם, asham, what רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
by the פסח? pesach? Shouldn't you be פטור patur when you do
it לשמה lishma because it is not fit? That is the question.
How is it different than the אשם? asham? And let's see the
answer. Let's see the answer and then I will take any questions
that you have. The גמרא Gemara says like this: It says, okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, לא שנו אלא שלא לשמה חייב לשמה
מיהא פטור. Lo shanu ella shelo lishma chayav lishma miha patur. So
for לשמה, lishma, it's you're still are exempt when you do the
אשם asham לשמה. lishma. אמאי נימא הוא וראוי שלא לשמה בפנים? Amai
nema ho varauy shelo lishma bifnim? The argument would be, now here's
the argument to say why you are חייב chayav for לשמה. lishma.
Yes, in this state, it would be פסול pasul in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but in theory, you could have changed its identity
by making it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. That's the argument to say
why you're חייב chayav even by לשמה, lishma, because in theory, you
could have done it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. But we don't say
that by the אשם. asham. Why should we say it by the
פסח? pesach? Why should we be מחייב mechayev you by the פסח
pesach when it's done לשמה, lishma, and by the אשם, asham, you're
get off the hook? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי השתא? Hachi
hashta? What type of a comparison is this? התם בעי עקירה. Hatam
baei akira. By the אשם, asham, the reason you're off the hook
is because you have to change its identity, that it is now
an אשם, asham, so therefore as long when you do it לשמה,
lishma, okay, meaning you have to hypothetically change its identity. If you
did the אשם, asham, okay, if the אשם, asham,
we say the same thing we say by the פסח. pesach. The
אשם asham לשמה, lishma, we say you're פטור patur and שלא לשמה
shelo lishma we say you are חייב. chayav. Okay, that's what we
said. Now, why are you פטור patur by לשמה? lishma? Can't you
theoretically make it into the שלא לשמה? shelo lishma? Shouldn't that obligate
you because theoretically you used to do a שלא לשמה? shelo lishma?
And it's like, yeah, theoretically you could, but that would entail changing
its identity. We're not going to be מחייב mechayev you for something
that you could have done had you changed its
identity. Okay? You're פטור. patur. You've kept it with its identity. In
this state, it's not fit for the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. You're
פטור. patur. We're not going to be מחייב mechayev you because you
could have theoretically
changed its identity. Who cares? Its current identity, you're פטור. patur. That's
why you're פטור. patur. התם בעי עקירה. Hatam baei akira. הכא פסח
בשאר ימות השנה שלמים
נינהו. Hacha pesach beshear yemot hashana shlamim ninhu. Here, you don't have
to change its identity. The natural status of a פסח pesach during
the rest of the year is a שלמים. shlamim. It's right now
not fit for a פסח, pesach, so it naturally is a שלמים.
shlamim. So the reason here you're חייב chayav when you do it
לשמה, lishma, according to רב ירמיה Rav Yirmeya and רב יוחנן, Rav
Yochanan, is because you could have done it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma.
But could have done it שלא לשמה shelo lishma doesn't mean you
could have changed its identity. It means you could have retained its
identity. Okay? So that's what they're saying. The reason here you're חייב
chayav is because you could have, if you would have let it
be a normal
פסח, pesach, just let the פסח pesach be normal, it would have
been שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. And therefore, you're חייב chayav because theoretically
you could have allowed it to be its normal status, and therefore
you would have been חייב. chayav. We don't say that here, because
here you would have to hypothetically change its status.
And you can't do that. התם קדושה שמה עקירה? Hatam kedusha shema
akira?
Well, no, that not necessarily. But you haven't done it. Okay. Please,
Michael. Okay, so I hope that was sort of clear enough.
Okay, yeah, I just wanted this to be very concrete. So I
take this animal, and I have the intent to שחט shacht it
one way, and then when I bring it בחוץ, bachutz, I say
out loud it's something else, that's שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. And what
do I actually do?
Yeah, meaning is it just a thought that goes through your head?
Do you have to verbalize it? That's a discussion way in the
beginning of זבחים, Zvachim, where it all talks about these things of
פיגול pigul and thinking this and thinking that, where pretty much רש"י
Rashi tells us both. So it means only when you verbalize it.
Okay, right. But so that's what we're talking about. Yeah, you're saying,
"I am doing this," right, "I am doing this for X. I'm
bringing this as a שלמים. shlamim. I'm bringing this as a whatever,"
exactly. Okay, alright, so we have all the range of possibilities. Again,
logically you would say פטור patur when you do the פסח pesach
לשמה lishma because it's not fit, שלא לשמה shelo lishma you're חייב.
chayav. You could say פטור patur in both cases, even שלא לשמה,
shelo lishma, you don't change its identity outside the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. You could say חייב chayav in both cases, even when you
do it לשמה. lishma. that won't get you off the hook because
its natural identity is a שלמים Shelamim and is fit for being
brought in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. רב אשי מתני חייב כדאמרינן. Rav Ashi masni
hayav k'damrinan.
רב אשי Rav Ashi teaches that you are חייב hayav in both
cases. רב ירמיה מדיפתי מתני פטור. Rav Yirmeya mi-Difti masni patur. רב
ירמיה Rav Yirmeya says you're פטור patur in both cases. קסבר פסח
בשאר ימות השנה בעי עקירה. Kasavar Pesach bi-shaar yemos ha-shana bei akira.
Number one he says its natural identity is not a שלמים. Shelamim.
To make it into a שלמים Shelamim you have to actively change
its identity. So that's why you are פטור patur when you do
it לשמו lishmo because its natural identity is still a פסח Pesach
so you're still off the hook. Why are you פטור patur when
you do it שלא לשמו? shelo lishmo? Hasn't that changed its identity?
No. עקירת חוץ לאו שמה עקירה. Akiras chutz lav shma akira. And
changing its identity doesn't work outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay?
So the reason to say פטור patur just reviewing that is to
say here you're obviously פטור patur because it's a פסח Pesach and
here you're פטור patur because it still its identity remains a פסח
Pesach
until you change its name and you cannot change its identity outside
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay? As opposed to חייב, hayav, which
says here you are here you're חייב hayav reasonably because you changed
its identity. Here you're חייב, hayav, the opposite, its natural identity is
a שלמים. Shelamim. So to get it even when you try to
get it to remain a פסח Pesach since in theory it could
have been its natural identity as a שלמים Shelamim you're going to
be חייב hayav in both cases. So part of this debate is
whether its default identity at now is a פסח Pesach or a
שלמים. Shelamim.
And it's פטור patur because עקירת חוץ
לאו שמה עקירה,
akira
chutz lav shma akira, right?
That's related, but yes. Okay. So אמר מר. Amar mar. Okay. ופליגא
דרב חלקיה בר
טובי, U-pliga di-Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi, רב אשי מתני... Rav Ashi masni...
I'm sorry, skipped a line. ופליגא דרב חלקיה בר טובי. U-pliga di-Rav
Hilkiya bar Tuvi. And it argues on רב חלקיה בר טובי Rav
Hilkiya bar Tuvi who by now I forgot what רב חלקיה בר
טובי Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi said. What did רב חלקיה בר טובי
Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi say? He goes up a few lines.
לא שנו אלא לשמו אבל שלא לשמו חייב. Lo shana ela lishmo
aval shelo lishmo hayav.
Oh, right, right, the case by the אשם, asham, exactly, because that's
this issue about עקירת חוץ. akiras chutz. Right, thank you. So רב
חלקיה בר טובי Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi by the אשם asham who
distinguishes לשמו lishmo and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo accepts עקירת חוץ akiras
chutz and therefore here you would have to, this position that says
you're פטור patur in both rejects עקירת חוץ. akiras chutz. Okay. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. All right. איש איש מבית ישראל אשר ישחט שור
או כשב או עז במחנה או אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה. Ish ish
mi-Beis Yisrael asher yishchat shor o kesev o ez ba-machane o asher
yishchat mi-chutz la-machane. Now we're going to, did I skip a line?
I'm sorry. אמר מר. Amar mar. משיעלו להם חייב על של שם
ופטור על של עזאזל. Mishiyu lo hem hayav al she-shem u-patur al
she-azazel. So now we're going to look at, that was before you
drew the lots. Why are you חייב? hayav? Because in theory it
could be used for the מוסף. musaf. Now we're going to get
after you draw the lots, you're חייב hayav on the one של
שם, she-shem, that's fit for אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, and not the
one לעזאזל, l'azazel, that's not going to be brought as a קרבן.
korban. Now we're going to see what some of the basis of
this is. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. איש איש
מבית ישראל אשר ישחט שור או כשב או עז במחנה או אשר
ישחט מחוץ למחנה ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו להקריב קרבן לה'
דם יחשב לאיש ההוא דם שפך ונכרת האיש ההוא
מקרב עמו. Ish ish mi-Beis Yisrael asher yishchat shor o kesev o
ez ba-machane o asher yishchat mi-chutz la-machane v'el pesach Ohel Moed lo
hevi'o l'hakriv korban l'Hashem dam yecha-shev la-ish ha-hu dam shafach v'nichras ha-ish
ha-hu mi-kerev amo. Okay, so
not good. You're שוחטי חוץ. shochtei chutz. או קרבן, O korban, now
what type of a thing are you חייב hayav for? It says
you did not bring it as a קרבן לה'. korban l'Hashem. או
קרבן, O korban, שומע אני אפילו קדשי בדק הבית, shomea ani afilu
kodshei bedek ha-bayis,
maybe you're חייב hayav even slaughtering things that are sanctified for their
value outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, not as a... why?
How would that be included in קרבן? korban? שנקראו קרבן, She-nikra'u korban,
they are called a קרבן. korban. כענין שנאמר ונקרב את קרבן ה',
K'inyan she-ne'emar v'nakriv es korban Hashem,
when they brought the donation, they called it a קרבן. korban. So
maybe it means even if you slaughter an animal that's a donation.
תלמוד לומר ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. Talmud lomar v'el pesach
Ohel Moed lo hevi'o.
You didn't bring it to the פתח אהל מועד. pesach Ohel Moed.
כל הראוי לפתח אהל מועד חייב עליו בחוץ. Kol ha-ra'uy l'pesach Ohel
Moed hayav alav ba-chutz. Only something that's fit for being brought to
the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, meaning not like you can't have animals
that are donations walking around there, but it's fit for אהל מועד
Ohel Moed means in the context of what does it mean to
bring something in the context of being brought as a קרבן, korban,
that there's significance to their being in the אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed.
כל שאינו ראוי לפתח אהל מועד אין חייבין עליו בחוץ. Kol she-eino
ra'uy l'pesach Ohel Moed ein hayavin alav ba-chutz. But if it's not
fit for that, it's not something that has to ritually be brought
into the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, meaning it's a donation and not
a קרבן, korban, then you are not חייב. hayav. Yes, what was
the question?
Sorry, I have a question. What's the context of קדשי בדק הבית?
kodshei bedek ha-bayis? Is it just any old דבר?
devar? Yeah. Yeah. I donate my... I can... it doesn't have to
be a kosher animal even. I can donate 20 of, you know,
my 20 donkeys as a donation to the בית... Beis... so what
if I slaughter them outside the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? So it
says no. Or let's say it's my 20 cows, but they're not
for קרבנות, korbanot, they're for working in the field. So that you're
not חייב hayav because that's not fit for אהל מועד. Ohel Moed.
They don't go to כהנים. kohanim. They...
no, no, no, they go... the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash sells it,
it goes to upkeep or whatever, everything we learned in שקלים. Shekalim.
Okay, various uses, the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash needed a lot of
funds. But anyway, but you're not חייב hayav if you slaughter them
because that's not fit for פתח אהל מועד, pesach Ohel Moed, that
doesn't have to ritually be brought into the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed.
Yes, Charlie? That...
this... these quotes are from the proscription of requiring all animals when
we're in the
מדבר... Midbar...
No, that's different. That is בשר תאוה. basar ta'avah. These פסוקים pesukim
are specifically אל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, el Pesach Ohel Moed
lo hevi'o, these are specifically about שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, not these
are not the פסוקים pesukim about that you have to eat meat
you have to bring it as a קרבן. korban. Okay? That's, yeah,
that's a different thing. This is specifically that it's sanctified and you
brought it as a קרבן korban outside. Because שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz,
because that issue was not a חייב כרת. chayav kareis. This is
דם יחשב דם שפך ונכרת האיש dam yeichashev dam shafach venichrat ha'ish
etc. This is about, so this is specifically about שחוטי חוץ, shchutei
chutz, okay? But you're right, they somewhat overlap at the time of,
at the time
the difference would be if you שחט shecht a non-sanctified animal outside
of the outside of the משכן. Mishkan. That would be the problem
of eating meat without bringing it as a קרבן korban that applied
in the מדבר. midbar. But this is about שחט shechting a sanctified
animal. Yes, please.
To me it seems that, you know, you're almost like ignoring the
טעמא דקרא. ta'ama dikra. The whole point is that you don't want
בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel to be bringing stuff outside. Here he's like,
oh well the פטור ptur is לשמו שלא לשמו. lishmo shelo lishmo.
He's like sort of like subverting the point.
Not subverting the point. Every law has its specifics its details. Right?
We don't want murder to occur, but in order to get somebody
to be, manslaughter's not murder.
It's like what we're doing here.
Right? Exactly. But you know so you what are you going to
do, moving on there's a next distinction, what, okay
obviously law needs detail specifics. We're moving on. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: הוציא את אלו שאינן פתח אהל מועד ולא
הוציא פר חטאת ושעיר המשתלח שהוא ראוי לבוא פתח אהל מועד. Hotzi
es elu she'einam Pesach Ohel Moed velo hotzi par chatas vesa'ir hamishtale'ach
shehu ra'uy lavo Pesach Ohel Moed. Maybe I'll exclude those that are
donations, but I won't exclude the case of the, of the cow
for פרה אדומה Parah Adumah or the שעיר sa'ir that gets sent
away because those are fit, I mean they come into אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. Now, רש"י Rashi says what do you mean פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah doesn't come into אהל מועד? Ohel Moed? So רש"י Rashi
cuts it, רש"י Rashi strikes it out. תוספות Tosafos sort of says
it's more like a parenthetical point. But we're going to focus on
this שעיר המשתלח. sa'ir hamishtale'ach. That is brought into אהל מועד Ohel
Moed for the drawing of lots. So it's not שחט shechted in
the אהל מועד Ohel Moed but it's brought in the אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. Maybe you'd be חייב chayav that if you שחט shechted
it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So שהוא ראוי לבוא פתח
אהל מועד, shehu ra'uy lavo Pesach Ohel Moed, תלמוד לומר לה' להקריב
קרבן לה'. talmud lomar l'Hashem lehakriv korban l'Hashem. You didn't bring it
as a קרבן korban to God. מי שמיוחדים לה', mi shemeyuchadim l'Hashem,
something that's all for God. יצאו אלו שאין מיוחדים לה' yatz'u elu
she'ein meyuchadim l'Hashem to exclude these which are not all for God,
it's לעזאזל. la'Azazel. Okay?
Now of course the שעיר לחטאת sa'ir lachatas is not לעזאזל, la'Azazel,
although it is interesting there's some discussion why is the שעיר חטאת
sa'ir chatas outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What does that
mean, a קרבן korban that is brought or a pseudo-קרבן korban that
is brought outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So if you actually
read this literally it actually suggests that idea that even the פר
חטאת par chatas for the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah has a not
fully לה' l'Hashem quality to it. The easier thing to say is
it just means it isn't being brought as a קרבן, korban, it
isn't fit for a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
The שעיר לעזאזל sa'ir la'Azazel or the חטאת chatas or whatever are
fit for things, their ritual takes place out of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So yes they have a קרבן korban status but as
קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash not in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay? ולה'
להוציא הוא? ul'Hashem l'hotzi hu? Okay,
does the word לה' l'Hashem come to exclude, saying these are not
fully לה', l'Hashem, so therefore the שעיר sa'ir is excluded and you're
not חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. I'm going to show
you where לה' l'Hashem comes to include the שעיר. sa'ir. רמיניה Ramini
I'll ask on this. ירצה לקרבן אשה לה'. yeratzeh lekorban isheh l'Hashem.
This is on day eight, you can bring something as a קרבן
korban but prior once the animal's eight days old. אלו אשים. elu
ishim. So number one it's telling you that only at that day
you can bring you can put it on the fire like the
limbs and the, you know, etc. you can burn it. Okay? But
less than that you cannot. מנין שלא יקדישנו מחוסר זמן? minayin shelo
yakdishenu mechussar zman? How do I know you're not even allowed to
sanctify it before it's eight days old? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, תלמוד
לומר קרבן. talmud lomar korban. So קרבן korban which רש"י Rashi which
somehow the word קרבן korban also means the act of sanctifying it.
Okay? From the moment you sanctify it's called a קרבן. korban. So
only on day eight can it be a קרבן, korban, prior it
cannot, prior you can't even sanctify. So what's
קרבן לה' ירצה לקרבן אשה לה'?
korban l'Hashem yeratzeh lekorban
isheh l'Hashem? מיום השמיני והלאה? miyom hashmini vehal'ah? לרבות שעיר המשתלח lerabbos
sa'ir hamishtale'ach that included in the prohibition of sanctifying before eight days
or using as a קרבן korban before eight days is the שעיר
המשתלח. sa'ir hamishtale'ach. Even though שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtale'ach is לעזאזל, la'Azazel,
not לה'. l'Hashem. So here's the question: can you use a goat
less than eight days old? Can you sanctify a goat less than
eight days old? So we learn from לה' l'Hashem that you cannot,
that it's excluded. So the גמרא Gemara says so what is it?
Does לה' l'Hashem include the שעיר לעזאזל, sa'ir la'Azazel, meaning meaning it's
included in the prohibition. So does the לה' l'Hashem include שעיר לעזאזל
sa'ir la'Azazel in the prohibition like it does by the eight days
old, or does it exclude it in the prohibition like it does
by the issue of שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz? Which is, so what's
the story? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא התם מעניינא דקרא
והכא מעניינא דקרא. Amar Rava hasam me'inyana dikra vehacha me'inyana dikra. In
each place you look at it in context of what the פסוק
pasuk is talking about. Okay, דהתם Dehatam
דאל פתח אהל מועד לרבות. De'al petach ohel moed l'rabos. When it's
saying that anything that hasn't been brought into the אהל מועד, Ohel
moed, so אל פתח, El petach, that would have naturally included the
שעיר Se'ir because the שעיר Se'ir is brought inside. You do a
ritual with the שעיר Se'ir inside, the drawing of the lots. So
therefore, if you already were including it, and then you have another
פסוק Pasuk לה', L'shem, that must be להוציא, L'hotzi, that must be
coming to tell you to make it to exclude because we anyway
we already were ready to include it. So now that you insist
לה', L'shem, you're telling me not the שעיר, Se'ir, which is לעזאזל.
L'azazel. הכא דאשה להוציא, Hacha de'isheh l'hotzi, here you start with a
narrower category. You speak about things that are burnt on the altar,
which would have naturally excluded the שעיר. לה', Se'ir L'shem, and then
you say לה', L'shem, that's coming to be more inclusive, לרבות. L'rabos.
Okay, it's coming to include. So basically, whatever the wherever your default
was, לה' L'shem, is going in the opposite direction. Okay, but what
we have here is, is that the שחוטי חוץ, Shechutei Chutz, the
שעיר Se'ir. is excluded because it was not going to be brought
as a קרבן, Korban, so you're exempt for שחוטי חוץ. Shechutei Chutz.
But where but the idea that you are that you cannot do
it less than eight days, there's a prohibition of doing it under
eight days, sanctifying it and using it and it's invalid, that includes
the שעיר לעזאזל, Se'ir L'azazel, there's לה' L'shem includes it and even
that cannot be less than eight days. Now the גמרא... Gemara... what?
How do we even get onto this topic?
Because we're talking about the שעיר, Se'ir because we're talking about the
two שעירים... Se'irim...
yeah correct, but we've run through the שעירים, Se'irim, talk about the
status outside the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and now the status of
מחוסר זמן. Mechusar zman. And this is actually going to lead to
a fun little piece of
גמרא, Gemara, the way I have fun. Okay, so let's take a
look. It says like this: טעמא דרבי ורחמנא. Ta'ama de'Rabbi v'Rachmana. So
the reason now you are saying that you can't use a goat
less than eight days old for the שעיר המשתלח Se'ir hamishtalei'ach is
because the תורה Torah included it in the prohibition. הלא רבי, Halo
Rabbi, if the תורה Torah had not included it in the prohibition,
הוה אמינא, Hava amina, I could have said שעיר המשתלח קדוש במחוסר
זמן, Se'ir hamishtalei'ach kadosh b'mechusar zman, that you could sanctify the שעיר
המשתלח, Se'ir hamishtalei'ach, maybe even use it less than eight days old.
It's not going לה', L'shem it's going לעזאזל, L'azazel, I would have
that's what
that was the hypothetical. Let me use an animal less than eight
days old for the שעיר המשתלח. Se'ir hamishtalei'ach. So the גמרא Gemara
says, how could you have done that? והא אין הגורל קובע אלא
בראוי לה'. Veha ein hagoral kovei'a ela b'ra'uy l'shem. You have to
have a lottery, and if you have a lottery, it means each
one has to theoretically be able to be used for the קרבן
Korban in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So even had there not
been a specific פסוק Pasuk to tell me it has to be
eight days old, I would have figured it out, because it each
goat has to be able in theory to be the one that's
going לה'. L'shem, So even if the לעזאזל L'azazel could be, there's
no way I can know ahead of time which is לעזאזל. L'azazel.
So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, הא מני חננא המצרי היא.
Ha manni Chanana Hamitzri hi. This is the חננא המצרי. Chanana Hamitzri.
דתניא, Detanya, חננא המצרי אומר, Chanana Hamitzri omer, אפילו דם בכוס מביא
חבירו ומזווג לו. Afilu dam bekos meivi chaveiro u'mezaveig lo.
Let's say you שחט Shechted the שעיר Se'ir, לה', L'shem. and then
the and you have the blood ready to do the ritual, and
then the שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir L'azazel drops dead. So you know what
he says? He says, okay, even with the blood in the cup,
go get another שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir L'azazel and pair it up. Go
get another goat and say, this now is the is the mate
of of this blood, you know, of the one that that was
used for this blood. So if you're go grabbing another goat and
now designating it as a שעיר לעזאזל, Se'ir L'azazel, there's no more
lottery. Now you know which one is שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir L'azazel. So
you have to tell me, don't make sure it's eight days old.
Right? You got the scenario? You're skipping the lottery. You did the
lottery, you got שחט Shechted it, you have the blood, and then
the other one died. So according to him, fine, just get another
goat and and have it have it be you don't do another
lottery, have it be an understudy. Oh, so there where I don't
have to do a lottery, maybe I would have said that could
be less that could be less than eight days old, and you
have to tell me not.
חננא המצרי Chanana Hamitzri for תנא... Tanna...
I know, it's interesting. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this: one
minute. אימא דשמעת ליה לחננא המצרי דלית ליה דחויה. Eima deshamat lei
l'Chanana Hamitzri d'leis lei dechuya. No, no, no, you you jumped too
far. All you know חננא המצרי Chanana Hamitzri said is is that
he doesn't have pushing off, meaning the blood did not become invalid
just because the other one died. דלית ליה הגרלה מי שמעת ליה?
D'leis lei hagrala mi shamat lei? He never said you don't have
to do another lottery. דילמא מייתי ומגריל, Dilma meiti u'magril, maybe you
do another lottery. Now what's the lottery with? The blood and the
goat? No. The lottery is, maybe he says you take two goats
and the one that that is לעזאזל, L'azazel, that becomes the substitute,
and the one that's לה' L'shem you let it graze, whatever you
do with it. Okay, so just because he says you get a
a mate, a pair for the blood, doesn't mean that you don't
have to do a lottery in order to identify the one that
is לעזאזל. L'azazel. So that's not a good example. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא אמר רב יוסף הא מני רבי שמעון היא. Ela
amar Rav Yosef ha manni Rabbi Shimon hi. It's רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. דתניא, Detanya, מת אחד מהם מביא חבירו שלא בהגרלה דברי רבי
שמעון. Met echad meihem meivi chaveiro shelo b'hagrala divrei Rabbi Shimon. That's
pretty straightforward. He says if one of the goats dies, get a
substitute and you can skip the lottery. Okay? So רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon actually explicitly says that you need to do the lottery initially,
but if something is if an animal has to come as an
understudy, as a substitute, then it doesn't need the lottery. Then it's
just filling the place of the other. So there is a scenario
where you could designate the לעזאזל... L'azazel... out without the lottery, and
therefore hypothetically, it could have been less than eight days old. רבינא
אמר, Ravina Amar, so we're now going to have other ways, interesting
possibilities where you can get the שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir L'Azazel and knowing
which one is the
שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir L'Azazel. רבינא אמר, Ravina Amar, כגון שהומם והפריש אחר.
k'gon shehumam v'hifrish acher. No, here's the scenario: the scenario is that
it's very similar, but this is the case here will allow without
a lottery. You have your שעיר לעזאזל, Se'ir L'Azazel, you did the
lottery, and now it got a blemish on it, so you can't
use it. So what do you have to do? So get another
goat and transfer the קדושה kedusha from this to the other one.
That's easier to understand why you don't need a lottery because that
really is a substitute of the one that's lost, actually is a
transfer of the קדושה kedusha of the other one, and that's the
scenario where you can get it without a lottery. Did we get
that? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to say, this
is what the גמרא Gemara is about to say. Now we get,
oh, that raises a new interesting question. So now we've dealt with
this issue of it has to be eight days old. Why do
I need to tell me eight days old? Couldn't I figure it
out that it has to be theoretically able to be להשם? L'Hashem?
And we gave a few examples of where you could designate the
שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir L'Azazel without the להשם, L'Hashem, designate it independently. Now
we've raised the issue that the שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir L'Azazel can't have
a blemish, so let's take a look at that.
ומנא תימא דפסול במום? u-mna teima d'pasul b'mum? Where do you know
that a blemish invalidates? דתניא, d'tanya, it was taught in a ברייתא,
Baraita, ואשה לא תתנו מהם אל המזבח לריח ניחוח. v'ishah lo titnu
mehem el hamizbeach l'reiach nichoach. This is by animals with a blemish:
don't put them as an burnt offering. אלו החלבים, elu hachalavim, fats,
don't burn their fats. אין לי אלא כולן, ein li ela kulan,
I only know don't burn all the fats. מקצתן מנין, miktsatan m'nayin,
how do I know don't even burn a little bit of the
fat? תלמוד לומר מהם, talmud lomar mehem, from them, nothing can go
on the fire. מזבח, mizbeach,
and it says ועל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. v'al hamizbeach lo
ya'alu l'reiach nichoach.
Don't put it on the altar. What does that mean? זו זריקת
דמים, zu zrikat damim, you can't throw the blood. You transgress a
prohibition if you do the throwing of the blood of an animal
with a blemish. להשם, L'Hashem, for God, so here's again להשם, L'Hashem,
לרבות שעיר המשתלח. l'rabot Se'ir HaMishtaleach. So now להשם L'Hashem is now
being more inclusive. So you can't, including even the שעיר, Se'ir, even
that cannot have a blemish. ואיצטריך למכתב בבעל מום ואיצטריך למכתב מחוסר
זמן. v'itztrich l'michtav b'ba'al mum v'itztrich l'michtav mechusar zman.
And so now what we're doing is, and this is a really
fascinating thing to think about. The שעיר Se'ir is לעזאזל. L'Azazel. How
much does it remains being thought of as a קרבן? korban? It's
not just like the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah which is outside the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. This seems to be going other than להשם,
L'Hashem, לעזאזל. L'Azazel. How much does that remain a concept of קרבן?
korban? So now we've made two requirements. Number one, it can't have
a blemish, and number two, it can't be מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman.
Okay, so both of those really are emphasizing its continued status as
קרבן. korban. And now we're going to say why you have to
say both.
Okay. ואי כתב רחמנא מחוסר זמן, v'ei katav Rachmana mechusar zman, had
it just said מחוסר זמן mechusar zman applies, משום דלא מטא זימניה,
mishum d'lo mta zimneh, that would make sense because it's, you know,
because it's not yet even old enough, it's not the right age.
So maybe that is a generic that applies to all. אבל בעל
מום דמטא זימניה, aval ba'al mum d'mta zimneh, בעל מום, ba'al mum,
which it is like the right age of the animal, it's just
a blemish. Maybe a blemish is only a problem for something that's
being brought as a קרבן. korban. אימא לא, eima lo, maybe not.
At least the animal is old enough. Maybe the blemish should not
be a problem. ואי כתב רחמנא בעל מום, v'ei katav Rachmana ba'al
mum, had it just excluded a בעל מום, ba'al mum, משום דמאיס,
mishum d'ma'is, that's a physical deformity, that makes it unfit. Okay. אבל
מחוסר זמן דלא מאיס, aval mechusar zman d'lo ma'is, but being too
young, that's not, that's not disgusting. אימא לא, eima lo, maybe it
shouldn't be a problem. צריכא. tzericha. So at the end of the
day, you have two פסוקים, psukim, you couldn't have inferred one. But
now we are making demands of the שעיר Se'ir not just because
it has to theoretically be able to be brought inside. Even when
it could be independent, the שעיר Se'ir has to be the right
age, no blemish, and that starts us off on thinking very seriously
about what is the nature of the of this whole שעיר לעזאזל,
Se'ir L'Azazel, you know, to what degree does it maintain this nature
of a
קרבן? korban?